<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="dtrust-tool">
	<refmeta>
		<refentrytitle>dtrust-tool</refentrytitle>
		<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
		<refmiscinfo class="productname">OpenSC</refmiscinfo>
		<refmiscinfo class="manual">OpenSC Tools</refmiscinfo>
		<refmiscinfo class="source">opensc</refmiscinfo>
	</refmeta>

	<refnamediv>
		<refname>dtrust-tool</refname>
		<refpurpose>
			displays information about D-Trust signature cards and remove the transport protection
		</refpurpose>
	</refnamediv>

	<refsynopsisdiv>
		<cmdsynopsis>
			<command>dtrust-tool</command>
			<arg choice="opt"><replaceable class="option">OPTIONS</replaceable></arg>
		</cmdsynopsis>
	</refsynopsisdiv>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Description</title>
		<para>
			The <command>dtrust-tool</command> utility is used to display information about
			D-Trust signature cards and to remove the initial transport protection.
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Options</title>
		<para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--check-transport-protection</option>,
						<option>-c</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							In the delivery state the card is locked by a so called
							transport protection. This option allows to check if the
							transport protection is still in force. The Signature PIN can
							only be used if the transport protection is removed.
						</para>

						<para>
							Initially the transport protection should be intact. If you
							receive a new card and the transport protection was already
							broken, don't use that card and contact the producer for
							further advice.
						</para>

						<para>
							If you removed the transport protection, it is normal that
							<command>dtrust-tool</command> reports the transport protection
							as broken. This is the normal operation state. It does not mean
							your card is broken.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--help</option>,
						<option>-h</option>
					</term>
					<listitem><para>Print help message on screen.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--reader</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>,
						<option>-r</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem><para>
						Number of the reader to use. By default, the first reader with a
						present card is used. If <replaceable>arg</replaceable> is an ATR, the
						reader with a matching card will be chosen.
					</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--pin-status</option>,
						<option>-s</option>
					</term>
					<listitem><para>
						Show the status of the various PINs. The Card Holder PIN is used for
						advanced signatures and decryption. It is only defined for signature
						cards, but not for sealing cards. The signature PIN is used for
						qualified signatures. It can only be used if it is unlocked by
						presenting the Transport PIN. Once the Transport PIN is used, it cannot
						be used anymore. The PUK is used to unlock PIN which had beend entered
						incorrectly several times.
					</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--unlock-transport-protection</option>,
						<option>-u</option>
					</term>
					<listitem><para>
						This command removes the transport protection. If first queries for the
						Transport PIN and then for the new value of the Signature PIN twice.
					</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--verbose</option>,
						<option>-v</option>
					</term>
					<listitem><para>
						Causes <command>dtrust-tool</command> to be more verbose. Specify this
						flag several times to enable debug output in the opensc library.
					</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--wait</option>,
						<option>-w</option>
					</term>
					<listitem><para>
						Causes <command>dtrust-tool</command> to wait for the token to be
						inserted into reader.
					</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Authors</title>
		<para><command>dtrust-tool</command> was written by
		Mario Haustein <email>mario.haustein@hrz.tu-chemnitz.de</email>.</para>
	</refsect1>
</refentry>
