<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry id="pkcs15-init">
	<refmeta>
		<refentrytitle>pkcs15-init</refentrytitle>
		<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
		<refmiscinfo class="productname">OpenSC</refmiscinfo>
		<refmiscinfo class="manual">OpenSC Tools</refmiscinfo>
		<refmiscinfo class="source">opensc</refmiscinfo>
	</refmeta>

	<refmeta>
		<refentrytitle>pkcs15-init</refentrytitle>
		<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
		<refmiscinfo class="productname">OpenSC</refmiscinfo>
		<refmiscinfo class="manual">OpenSC Tools</refmiscinfo>
		<refmiscinfo class="source">opensc</refmiscinfo>
	</refmeta>

	<refnamediv>
		<refname>pkcs15-init</refname>
		<refpurpose>smart card personalization utility</refpurpose>
	</refnamediv>

	<refsynopsisdiv>
		<cmdsynopsis>
			<command>pkcs15-init</command>
			<arg choice="opt"><replaceable class="option">OPTIONS</replaceable></arg>
		</cmdsynopsis>
	</refsynopsisdiv>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Description</title>
		<para>
			The <command>pkcs15-init</command> utility can be used to create a PKCS #15
			structure on a smart card, and add key or certificate objects. Details of the
			structure that will be created are controlled via profiles.
		</para>
		<para>
			The profile used by default is <command>pkcs15</command>. Alternative
			profiles can be specified via the <option>-p</option> switch.
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>PIN Usage</title>
		<para>
			<command>pkcs15-init</command> can be used to create a PKCS #15 structure on
			your smart card, create PINs, and install keys and certificates on the card.
			This process is also called <replaceable>personalization</replaceable>.
		</para>
		<para>
			An OpenSC card can have one security officer PIN, and zero or more user PINs.
			PIN stands for Personal Identification Number, and is a secret code you need
			to present to the card before being allowed to perform certain operations,
			such as using one of the stored RSA keys to sign a document, or modifying
			the card itself.
		</para>
		<para>
			Usually, PINs are a sequence of decimal digits, but some cards will accept
			arbitrary ASCII characters. Be aware however that using characters other
			than digits will make the card unusable with PIN pad readers, because those
			usually have keys for entering digits only.
		</para>
		<para>
			The security officer (SO) PIN is special; it is used to protect meta data
			information on the card, such as the PKCS #15 structure itself. Setting
			the SO PIN is optional, because the worst that can usually happen is that
			someone finding your card can mess it up. To extract any of your secret
			keys stored on the card, an attacker will still need your user PIN, at
			least for the default OpenSC profiles. However, it is possible to create
			card profiles that will allow the security officer to override user PINs.
		</para>
		<para>
			For each PIN, you can specify a PUK (also called <replaceable>unblock PIN</replaceable>).
			The PUK can be used to overwrite or unlock a PIN if too many incorrect values
			have been entered in a row.
		</para>
		<para>
			For some cards that use the PKCS#15 emulation, the attributes of private objects
			are protected and cannot be parsed without authentication (usually with User PIN).
			This authentication need to be done immediately after the card binding.
			In such cases <option>--verify-pin</option> has to be used.
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Modes of operation</title>
		<refsect2>
			<title>Initialization</title>
			<para>This is the first step during card personalization, and will create the
				basic files on the card. To create the initial PKCS #15 structure, invoke the
				utility as
			</para>
			<para>
				<command>pkcs15-init --create-pkcs15</command></para>
			<para>
				You will then be asked for the security officer PIN and PUK. Simply
				pressing return at the SO PIN prompt will skip installation of an SO PIN.
			</para>
			<para>
				If the card supports it, you should erase the contents of the card with
				<command>pkcs15-init --erase-card</command> before creating the PKCS#15 structure.
			</para>
		</refsect2>

		<refsect2>
			<title>User PIN Installation</title>
			<para>
				Before installing any user objects such as private keys, you need at least one
				PIN to protect these objects. you can do this using
			</para>
			<para>
				<command>pkcs15-init --store-pin --id " nn</command>
			</para>
			<para>
				where <replaceable>nn</replaceable> is a PKCS #15 ID in hexadecimal notation. Common
				values are 01, 02, etc.
			</para>
			<para>
				Entering the command above will ask you for the user's PIN and PUK. If you do
				not wish to install an unblock PIN, simply press return at the PUK prompt.
			</para>
			<para>
				To set a label for this PIN object (which can be used by applications to display
				a meaningful prompt to the user), use the <option>--label</option> command line option.
			</para>
		</refsect2>

		<refsect2>
			<title>Key generation</title>
			<para>
				<command>pkcs15-init</command> lets you generate a new key and store it on the card.
				You can do this using:
			</para>
			<para>
				<command>pkcs15-init --generate-key " keyspec " --auth-id " nn</command>
			</para>
			<para>
				where <replaceable>keyspec</replaceable> describes the algorithm and length of the
				key to be created, such as <literal>rsa/512</literal>. This will create a 512 bit
				RSA key. Currently, only RSA key generation is supported. Note that cards
				usually support just a few different key lengths. Almost all cards will support
				512 and 1024 bit keys, some will support 768 or 2048 as well.
			</para>
			<para>
				<replaceable>nn</replaceable> is the ID of a user PIN installed previously,
				e.g. <literal>01</literal>.
			</para>
			<para>
				In addition to storing the private portion of the key on the card,
				<command>pkcs15-init</command> will also store the public portion of the
				key as a PKCS #15 public key object.
			</para>
		</refsect2>

		<refsect2>
			<title>Private Key Upload</title>
			<para>
				You can use a private key generated by other means and upload it to the card.
				For instance, to upload a private key contained in a file named
				<filename>okir.pem</filename>, which is in PEM format, you would use
			</para>
			<para>
				<command>pkcs15-init --store-private-key okir.pem --id 45 --auth-id 01</command>
			</para>
			<para>
				In addition to storing the private portion of the key on the card,
				<command>pkcs15-init</command> will also store the public portion of the
				key as a PKCS #15 public key object.
			</para>
			<para>
				Note that usage of <option>--id</option> option in the <command>pkcs15-init</command>
				commands to generate or to import a new key is deprecated.
				Better practice is to let the middleware to derive the identifier from the key material.
				(SHA1(modulus) for RSA, SHA1(pub) for DSA, ...).
				This allows easily set up relation between 'related' objects
				(private/public keys and certificates).
			</para>
			<para>
				In addition to the PEM key file format, <command>pkcs15-init</command> also
				supports DER encoded keys, and PKCS #12 files. The latter is the file format
				used by Netscape Navigator (among others) when exporting certificates to
				a file. A PKCS #12 file usually contains the X.509 certificate corresponding
				to the private key. If that is the case, <command>pkcs15-init</command> will
				store the certificate instead of the public key portion.
			</para>
		</refsect2>

		<refsect2>
			<title>Public Key Upload</title>
			<para>
				You can also upload individual public keys to the card using the
				<option>--store-public-key</option> option, which takes a filename as an
				argument. This file is supposed to contain the public key. If you don't
				specify a key file format using the <option>--format</option> option,
				<command>pkcs15-init</command> will assume PEM format. The only other
				supported public key file format is DER.
			</para>
			<para>
				Since the corresponding public keys are always uploaded automatically
				when generating a new key, or when uploading a private key, you will
				probably use this option only very rarely.
			</para>
		</refsect2>

		<refsect2>
			<title>Certificate Upload</title>
			<para>
				You can upload certificates to the card using the
				<option>--store-certificate</option> option, which takes a filename as
				an argument. This file is supposed to contain the PEM encoded X.509
				certificate.
			</para>
		</refsect2>

		<refsect2>
			<title>Uploading PKCS #12 bags</title>
			<para>
				Most browsers nowadays use PKCS #12 format files when you ask them to
				export your key and certificate to a file. <command>pkcs15-init</command>
				is capable of parsing these files, and storing their contents on the
				card in a single operation. This works just like storing a private key,
				except that you need to specify the file format:
			</para>
			<para>
				<command>pkcs15-init --store-private-key okir.p12 --format pkcs12 --auth-id
				01</command>
			</para>
			<para>
				This will install the private key contained in the file <filename>okir.p12</filename>,
				and protect it with the PIN referenced by authentication ID <literal>01</literal>.
				It will also store any X.509 certificates contained in the file, which is
				usually the user certificate that goes with the key, as well as the CA certificate.
			</para>
		</refsect2>

		<refsect2>
			<title>Secret Key Upload</title>
			<para>
				You can use a secret key generated by other means and upload it to the card.
				For instance, to upload an AES-secret key generated by the system random generator
				you would use
			</para>
			<para>
				<command>pkcs15-init --store-secret-key /dev/urandom --secret-key-algorithm aes/256 --auth-id 01</command>
			</para>
			<para>
				By default a random ID is generated for the secret key. You may specify an ID
				with the <option>--id</option> if needed.
			</para>
		</refsect2>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Options</title>
		<para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--version</option>,
					</term>
					<listitem><para>Print the OpenSC package release version.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--card-profile</option> <replaceable>name</replaceable>,
						<option>-c</option> <replaceable>name</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to load the specified card
							profile option. You will rarely need this option.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--create-pkcs15</option>,
						<option>-C</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							This tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to create a PKCS #15
							structure on the card, and initialize any PINs.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--serial</option> <replaceable>SERIAL</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Specify the serial number of the card.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--erase-card</option>,
						<option>-E</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							This will erase the card prior to creating the PKCS #15 structure,
							if the card supports it. If the card does not support erasing,
							<command>pkcs15-init</command> will fail.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--erase-application</option> <replaceable>AID</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							This will erase the application with the application identifier
							<replaceable>AID</replaceable>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--generate-key</option> <replaceable>keyspec</replaceable>,
						<option>-G</option> <replaceable>keyspec</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells the card to generate new key and store it on the card.
							<replaceable>keyspec</replaceable> consists of an algorithm name
							(currently, the only supported name is <option>RSA</option>),
							optionally followed by a slash and the length of the key in bits.
							It is a good idea to specify the key ID along with this command,
							using the <option>id</option> option, otherwise an intrinsic ID
							will be calculated from the key material. Look the description of
							the 'pkcs15-id-style' attribute in the 'pkcs15.profile' for the details
							about the algorithm used to calculate intrinsic ID.
							For the multi-application cards the target PKCS#15 application can be
							specified by the hexadecimal AID value of the <option>aid</option> option.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--options-file</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to read additional options
							from <replaceable>filename</replaceable>. The file is supposed to
							contain one long option per line, without the leading dashes,
							for instance:
							<programlisting>
pin		1234
puk		87654321
							</programlisting>
						</para>
						<para>
							You can specify <option>--options-file</option> several times.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--pin</option>,
						<option>--puk</option>
						<option>--so-pin</option>,
						<option>--so-puk</option>,
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							These options can be used to specify PIN/PUK values
							on the command line. If set to
							env:<replaceable>VARIABLE</replaceable>, the value
							of the environment variable
							<replaceable>VARIABLE</replaceable> is used. Note
							that on most operation systems, any user can
							display the command line of any process on the
							system using utilities such as
							<command>ps(1)</command>. Therefore, you should use
							these options only on a secured system, or in an
							options file specified with
							<option>--options-file</option>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--no-so-pin</option>,
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Do not install a SO PIN, and do not prompt for it.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--profile</option> <replaceable>name</replaceable>,
						<option>-p</option> <replaceable>name</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to load the specified general
							profile. Currently, the only application profile defined is
							<literal>pkcs15</literal>, but you can write your own profiles and
							specify them using this option.
						</para>
						<para>
							The profile name can be combined with one or more profile
							options, which slightly modify the profile's behavior.
							For instance, the default OpenSC profile supports the
							<option>openpin</option> option, which installs a single PIN during
							card initialization. This PIN is then used both as the SO PIN as
							well as the user PIN for all keys stored on the card.
						</para>
						<para>
							Profile name and options are separated by a <literal>+</literal>
							character, as in <literal>pkcs15+onepin</literal>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--secret-key-algorithm</option> <replaceable>keyspec</replaceable>,
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<replaceable>keyspec</replaceable> describes the algorithm and length of the
							key to be created or downloaded, such as <literal>aes/256</literal>.
							This will create a 256 bit AES key.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--store-certificate</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>,
						<option>-X</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to store the certificate given
							in <option>filename</option> on the card, creating a certificate
							object with the ID specified via the <option>--id</option> option.
							Without supplied ID an intrinsic ID will be calculated from the
							certificate's public key. Look the description of the 'pkcs15-id-style'
							attribute in the 'pkcs15.profile' for the details
							about the algorithm used to calculate intrinsic ID.
							The file is assumed to contain the PEM encoded certificate.
							For the multi-application cards the target application can be specified
							by the hexadecimal AID value of the <option>aid</option> option.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--store-pin</option>,
						<option>-P</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Store a new PIN/PUK on the card.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--store-public-key</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to download the specified
							public key to the card and create a public key object with the
							key ID specified via the <option>--id</option>. By default,
							the file is assumed to contain the key in PEM format. Alternative
							formats can be specified using <option>--format</option>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--store-private-key</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>,
						<option>-S</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to download the specified
							private key to the card. This command will also create a public
							key object containing the public key portion. By default, the
							file is assumed to contain the key in PEM format. Alternative
							formats can be specified using <option>--format</option>.
							It is a good idea to specify the key ID along with this command,
							using the <option>--id</option> option, otherwise an intrinsic ID
							will be calculated from the key material. Look the description of
							the 'pkcs15-id-style' attribute in the 'pkcs15.profile' for the details
							about the algorithm used to calculate intrinsic ID.
							For the multi-application cards the target PKCS#15 application can be
							specified by the hexadecimal AID value of the <option>aid</option> option.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--store-secret-key</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>,
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to download the specified
							secret key to the card. The file is assumed to contain the raw key.
							They key type should be specified with <option>--secret-key-algorithm</option>
							option.
						</para>
						<para>
							You may additionally specify the key ID along with this command,
							using the <option>--id</option> option, otherwise a random ID is generated.
							For the multi-application cards the target PKCS#15 application can be
							specified by the hexadecimal AID value of the <option>aid</option> option.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--store-data</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>,
						<option>-W</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Store a data object.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--update-certificate</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>,
						<option>-U</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to update the certificate
							object with the ID specified via the <option>--id</option> option
							with the certificate in <replaceable>filename</replaceable>.
							The file is assumed to contain a PEM encoded certificate.
						</para>
						<para>Pay extra attention when updating mail decryption certificates, as
							missing certificates can render e-mail messages unreadable!
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--delete-objects</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>,
						<option>-D</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to delete the
							specified object.  <replaceable>arg</replaceable>
							is comma-separated list containing any of
							<literal>privkey</literal>, <literal>pubkey</literal>,
							<literal>secrkey</literal>, <literal>cert</literal>,
							<literal>chain</literal> or <literal>data</literal>.
						</para>
						<para>
							When <literal>data</literal> is specified, an
							-<option>--application-id</option> must also be
							specified, in the other cases an
							<option>--id</option> must also be specified
						</para>
						<para>
							When <literal>chain</literal> is specified, the
							certificate chain starting with the cert with
							specified ID will be deleted, until there's a CA
							certificate that certifies another cert on the card
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--change-attributes</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>,
						<option>-A</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to change the
							specified attribute. <replaceable>arg</replaceable>
							is either <literal>privkey</literal>,
							<literal>pubkey</literal>, <literal>secrkey</literal>,
							<literal>cert</literal> or <literal>data</literal>.
							You also have to specify the <option>--id</option>
							of the object.
							For now, you can only change the <option>--label</option>, e.g:
							<programlisting>
								pkcs15-init -A cert --id 45 -a 1 --label Jim
							</programlisting>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--use-default-transport-keys</option>,
						<option>-T</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to not ask for the transport
							keys and use default keys, as known by the card driver.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--sanity-check</option>,
						<option>-T</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Tells <command>pkcs15-init</command> to perform a
							card specific sanity check and possibly update
							procedure.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--reader</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>,
						<option>-r</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Number of the reader to use. By default, the first
							reader with a present card is used. If
							<replaceable>arg</replaceable> is an ATR, the
							reader with a matching card will be chosen.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--verbose</option>,
						<option>-v</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Causes <command>pkcs15-init</command> to be more verbose. Specify this
							flag several times to enable debug output in the OpenSC library.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--wait</option>,
						<option>-w</option>
					</term>
					<listitem><para>Causes <command>pkcs15-init</command> to
							wait for a card insertion.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--use-pinpad</option>
					</term>
					<listitem><para>Do not prompt the user; if no PINs supplied, pinpad will be used.</para></listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--puk-id</option> <replaceable>ID</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Specify ID of PUK to use/create
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--puk-label</option> <replaceable>LABEL</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Specify label of PUK
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--public-key-label</option> <replaceable>LABEL</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Specify public key label (use with <option>--generate-key</option>)
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--cert-label</option> <replaceable>LABEL</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Specify user cert label (use with <option>--store-private-key</option>)
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--application-name</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Specify application name of data object (use with <option>--store-data-object</option>)
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--aid</option> <replaceable>AID</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Specify AID of the on-card PKCS#15 application to be binded to (in hexadecimal form)
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--output-file</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
						<option>-o</option> <replaceable>filename</replaceable>,
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Output public portion of generated key to file
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--passphrase</option> <replaceable>PASSPHRASE</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Specify passphrase for unlocking secret key
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--authority</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Mark certificate as a CA certificate
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--key-usage</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>
						<option>-u</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>,
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Specifies the X.509 key usage.
							<replaceable>arg</replaceable> is comma-separated
							list containing any of
							<literal>digitalSignature</literal>,
							<literal>nonRepudiation</literal>,
							<literal>keyEncipherment</literal>,
							<literal>dataEncipherment</literal>,
							<literal>keyAgreement</literal>,
							<literal>keyCertSign</literal>,
							<literal>cRLSign</literal>. Abbreviated names are
							allowed if unique (e.g.
							<literal>dataEnc</literal>).
						</para>
						<para>
							The alias <literal>sign</literal> is equivalent to
							<literal>digitalSignature,keyCertSign,cRLSign</literal>
						</para>
						<para>
							The alias <literal>decrypt</literal> is equivalent to
							<literal>keyEncipherment,dataEncipherment</literal>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--finalize</option>
						<option>-F</option>,
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Finish initialization phase of the smart card
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--update-last-update</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Update 'lastUpdate' attribute of tokenInfo
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--ignore-ca-certificates</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							When storing PKCS#12 ignore CA certificates
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--update-existing</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Store or update existing certificate
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--extractable</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Private key stored as an extractable key
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

                                <varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--user-consent</option> <replaceable>arg</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Specify user-consent. <replaceable>arg</replaceable> is an integer value.
                                                        If > 0, the value specifies how many times the
                                                        object can be accessed before a new authentication is required.
                                                        If zero, the object does not require re-authentication.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--insecure</option>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Insecure mode: do not require a PIN for private key
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--md-container-guid</option> <replaceable>GUID</replaceable>
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							For a new key specify GUID for a MD container
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>
						<option>--help</option>
						<option>-h</option>,
					</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Display help message
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

			</variablelist>
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>See also</title>
		<para>
			<citerefentry>
				<refentrytitle>pkcs15-profile</refentrytitle>
				<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
			</citerefentry>
		</para>
	</refsect1>

	<refsect1>
		<title>Authors</title>
		<para><command>pkcs15-init</command> was written by
		Olaf Kirch <email>okir@suse.de</email>.</para>
	</refsect1>

</refentry>
